<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Rails | Drafts Previewer]]></title>
  <link href="http://vis-kid.github.io/octopress_drafts_previewer/blog/categories/rails/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://vis-kid.github.io/octopress_drafts_previewer/"/>
  <updated>2015-11-11T17:33:52+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://vis-kid.github.io/octopress_drafts_previewer/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Your Name]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Middleman Basics 01]]></title>
    <link href="http://vis-kid.github.io/octopress_drafts_previewer/blog/2015/11/05/Middleman-01/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-05T04:29:10+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://vis-kid.github.io/octopress_drafts_previewer/blog/2015/11/05/Middleman-01</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/middleman/Three_Stooges_1959.jpg"></p>

<h3>Topics</h3>

<ul>
<li>Middleman &amp; Static Pages</li>
<li>Installation &amp; Getting Started</li>
<li>Configuration</li>
<li>A new Site</li>
<li>Source vs Build vs Deploy(GitHub Pages)</li>
<li>Structure</li>
<li>Frontmatter</li>
<li>Templating</li>
<li>Helpers</li>
<li>Layouts</li>
<li>Partials</li>
<li><p>Extensions</p></li>
<li><h3>Middleman &amp; Static Pages</h3></li>
</ul>


<p>What’s all the fuzz lately with static sites? Easy, they’re fast, pretty straightforward to set up and lightweight I’d say. Because you’re not serving anything database related, static sites are pretty reliable and speedy. HTML, CSS and JS—that’s all. What’s it for? Well, a lot of people use it to set up their blogs and personal pages. Landing pages that are hit by traffic heavily are also a good candidate. <a href="https://www.healthcare.gov/">HealthCare.gov</a> from the Obama administration famously used Jekyll, another static site generator, for their site. Its not a Swiss Army knife for every purpose but if you need something quick and easy that is able to scale out of the box, static sites can be amazing. Especially if you can host them for free on <a href="https://pages.github.com/">GitHub Pages</a> or <a href="https://www.heroku.com/">Heroku</a>.</p>

<p>I guess the whole static site hipness got slowly started a few years back when <a href="http://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</a> came along. Of course, static sites are as old as the first “Hello World!” from Sir Tim Berners-Lee but over the past 15 years, database backed apps were mostly “all that mattered”. Couple of years back, one of the co-founders of GitHub needed a better way to write blogs and he came up with Jekyll—this hip static site generator for “Blogging like a hacker”. Its pretty amazing! I’ve used it on a couple of occasions and have only good things to report. The core team is awesome too. Anyhow, for this series my editor and I agreed it would be more interesting to cover <a href="https://middlemanapp.com/">Middleman</a>. It might be fair to say that Middleman is a bit less “blog-aware” out of the box but none the less equally as powerful and great quality-wise.</p>

<p>Middleman uses Ruby and offers a pretty extensive set of features to build cool stuff. Couple of my favorite blogs use Middleman. If you’ve ever used Rails or Sinatra you’ll feel right at home. It seems Middleman and Jekyll are the go-to options for static sites in the Ruby community. I have heard more and more designers argue that they like using them too—for prototyping and for setting up their own personal pages. What a lot of these static site frameworks have in common is that they are pretty straightforward to use. I actually believe its a good idea to teach people coding by playing with one of these ruby based static site frameworks—instead of jumping into Rails or Sinatra right away. (Sure, Sinatra is small too but there are still more concepts at work compared to Middleman for example.) Next time someone wants to learn to program in Ruby and asks me for directions I’ll probably point them towards Middleman or Jekyll.</p>

<p>So in this article I’ll assume that you are at least a bit interested in Ruby and have it installed on your system. Knowing how to deal with RubyGems is necessary too. I’ll do my best to not go over your head with programming concepts but I won’t cover basics like loops, code blocks and such. For the newbies among you, don’t worry, Middleman has not that many moving parts or tons of magic—not that I’m one of those magic naggers—and they I believe its easy to learn too.</p>

<ul>
<li><h3>Installation &amp; Getting Started</h3></li>
</ul>


<p>So you got Ruby and RubyGems under your belt? Great, then we’re good to go.</p>

<p>Terminal:</p>

<pre><code class="bash">gem install middleman
</code></pre>

<p>After this process has finished, you’ll be able to use a couple of handy commands in your shell.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>middleman init</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>This command initiates a new project—you just have to provide it with the name of your app.</p>

<p>Terminal:</p>

<pre><code class="bash">middleman init your_fancy_app
</code></pre>

<p>It also takes additional arguments like which template you wanna start with. This makes it really handy to customize your apps with templates right from the start—cuts down on repetetive setup tasks quite a bit! There are a couple ones ready out of the box—like one for blogs for example and you can use your own custom ones too of course. More on that in a later article.</p>

<p>Terminal:</p>

<pre><code class="bash ">middleman init your_fancy_blog --template=blog
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="bash">middleman init your_fancy_mobile_app --template=mobile
</code></pre>

<ul>
<li><strong>middleman server</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>Middleman comes with a local server for your development. Starting it up lets you see your site at <strong><a href="http://localhost:4567/">http://localhost:4567/</a> </strong>. If you just type <strong>middleman</strong> without any additional argument, your server gets also fired up. Shut down your server with <strong>CTRL-c</strong>.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>middleman build</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>Once you have something you are ready to put on an internet-facing server you need to <strong>build</strong> your site. That means that whatever you have prepared in your <strong>/source</strong> folder gets processed and the final output goes into the <strong>/build</strong> folder that middleman also creates for you. All your files that use preprocessors like <a href="http://slim-lang.com/about.html">Slim</a>, <a href="http://haml.info/">Haml</a>, <a href="http://sass-lang.com/">Sass</a>, <a href="http://coffeescript.org/">CoffeeScript</a> get translated into their respective counterparts and put into your /build directory which your server will host.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>middleman deploy</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>Once your site is ready to face the internet, this command deploys your <strong>/build</strong> folder onto your web server. So every update you have finished goes through that process. Its the equivalent to depoying with Git to Heroku if you have played with that in the past.</p>

<h4>Attention!</h4>

<p>Do yourself a favor right away and activate <a href="http://livereload.com/">LiveReload</a> to instantly refresh your pages automatically after changes to your HTML, Sass or JS files. This is of great convenience during development—you won’t regret it! In the past it was sometimes a pain to set up but Middleman offers <em>LiveReload</em> out of the box—you just need to uncomment the following line in <strong>config.rb</strong>:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby"># Reload the browser automatically whenever files change
activate :livereload
</code></pre>

<ul>
<li><h3>Source vs Build vs Deploy(GitHub Pages)</h3></li>
</ul>


<p>So let’s get get started with <strong>/source</strong> and <strong>/build</strong> folders. Between them is the dividing line that separates your development and production sections. When you use your local web server for development, /source gets used to serve your app. The /build folder is used by your non-local servers to serve your static pages. /build gets created every time you use <strong>middleman build</strong> in your command line. Therefore you should be careful to not accidentally spend your time coding in /build because it will disappear after the build process. Sure there is Git if you’re lucky but in general, all your development is supposed to happen in /source.</p>

<p>The build process creates the static sites that you want your server to host. Each file in your <strong>/source</strong> folder will get processed and then stored in <strong>/build</strong>. That means that your Sass, CoffeeScript, Slim / Haml and partials will translante themselves into CSS, JavaScript and HTML files. All the layouts will be pieced together as well. If you have activated compression for these files, this is the moment they get “uglified” too. During this whole shabang, the /build folder gets rejuvinated by getting rid of files that have no reference in /source anymore. During <strong>middleman build</strong>, any changes you made to files in /source will trigger a regeneration of new corresponding static files for /build.</p>

<p>The deployment process is the last step. With the <strong>/build</strong> directory in place you have everything you need to put your app out there. My recommendation is to do this early and avoid running into any surprises. I’ll show you how to deploy via <a href="https://pages.github.com/">GitHub Pages</a>. You’ll see, it couldn’t be any easier or more convenient. Assuming that you already initiated Git (<strong>git init</strong>) It’s basically five simple steps:</p>

<h3>Project Page For Users &amp; Organizations</h3>

<h4>Step 00</h4>

<p>We’ll need to start with adding a Gem for deployment to your <strong>Gemfile</strong>:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">gem "middleman-deploy"
</code></pre>

<h4>Step 01</h4>

<p>In your terminal run</p>

<pre><code class="bash">bundle install
</code></pre>

<h4>Step 02</h4>

<p>Open your <strong>config.rb</strong> file and add the following:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">activate :deploy do |deploy|
  deploy.method = :git
  deploy.branch = 'gh-pages'
  deploy.build_before = true
end
</code></pre>

<h4>Attention!</h4>

<p>The most important bit is the branch <code>'gh-pages</code>. That way you can setup a <strong>prject page</strong> which means that for every repo you can possibly have your own GitHub pages page. Prettty neat!</p>

<h4>Step 03</h4>

<p>Create a new repository on GitHub and add the remote branch—so everthing you’d normally do when you follow GitHub’s instructions.</p>

<pre><code class="bash">git remote add origin https://github.com/yourusername/repositoryname.git
</code></pre>

<p>If you want you can back up your master branch the same way as always too.
(optional):</p>

<pre><code class="bash">git push -u origin master
</code></pre>

<h4>Step 04</h4>

<pre><code class="bash">middleman deploy
</code></pre>

<p>Boom, that’s it! If you forget to run <strong>middleman build</strong>, with this setup the build process gets initiated automatically before the files in <strong>/build</strong> get deployed to GitHub Pages. Once you’re finished you’ll find your app under <code>username.github.io/projectname</code> or <code>organisationname.github.io/projectname</code> for organizations.</p>

<p>You now have a <strong>gh-pages</strong> branch on GitHub which is used for serving your app. If you have optionally pushed your master branch also then it will be there too of course. At its most basic, this branch consists of the following folders:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>/images</strong></li>
<li><strong>/javascripts</strong></li>
<li><strong>/stylesheets</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>and an <strong>index.html</strong> file.</p>

<h3>User &amp; Organization Pages</h3>

<p>If you want your middleman app to be a <em>User</em> or <em>Organization</em> page on GitHub Pages you’d need to change a little bit of configuration that is concerned with the deploy branch. These pages reside under your <code>username.github.io</code>—why you obviously can only have one of these pages. Quite honestly I don’t see the need for these, after all you’d set up your own domain name for it anyway if the app is of any importance to you. Therefore I’ll stop here and let you figure this out on your own if you find a good reason not to use plain project pages. Its not tricky or anything, the main differnce is that the content from your master branch is used to build and publish this page for you.</p>

<ul>
<li><h3>Skelleton Structure</h3></li>
</ul>


<p>Let’s check out the basic structure of a Middleman app. The main components are:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>/images</strong></li>
<li><strong>/javascripts</strong></li>
<li><strong>/layouts</strong></li>
<li><strong>/stylesheets</strong></li>
<li><strong>config.rb</strong></li>
<li><strong>An index.html.erb file</strong></li>
<li><strong>A Gemfile</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>As you see below, the most Jazz goes into the <strong>/source</strong> folder. What I like about Middleman apps is their simple organization—even if you are a newbie, its pretty hard to get lost in here. One of the reasons I recommend beginners to play with Middleman first.</p>

<h4>Screenshot:</h4>

<p><img src="/images/middleman/source_structure.png"></p>

<p>If you are unhappy with the naming of some of these folders you can change that in your configurations (<strong>config.rb</strong>) of course. The same names will be used then for your finished <strong>/build</strong> folder.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">set :css_dir,    'custom_foler_name'

set :js_dir,     'custom_foler_name'

set :images_dir, 'custom_foler_name'
</code></pre>

<p>When you have your server running, you can check out other options to configure Middleman right in your browser: <a href="http://localhost:4567/__middleman/config/.">http://localhost:4567/__middleman/config/.</a> Not all of them might make sense or are even important to know. Give it a glance and a mental bookmark is totally sufficient for now.</p>

<p>One you run <strong>middleman build</strong> you can peak into the <strong>/build</strong> folder. All the plain HTML, CSS and JS files you need to serve your static site.</p>

<p><img src="/images/middleman/build_structure.png"></p>

<p>That’s pretty much all you need to know to get started and to orient yourself.</p>

<ul>
<li><h3>Frontmatter</h3></li>
</ul>


<p>I know, naming is hard! Anyway, every page allows you to have variables that can be stored right at the top inside a leading and a trailing triple hyphen—3 minus signs top and bottom. I’ll show you:</p>

<p><strong>some.html.erb</strong></p>

<h2>``` erb</h2>

<p>layout: Bond
title:  Favorite bond girl names
date:   2015-11-09
tags:   bond, 007</p>

<p>some_secret: I won’t get rendered until you use me.</p>

<p>bond_girls:
  - Strawberry Fields
  - Jill Masterson
  - Tiffany Case</p>

<hr />

<h1>Top three names for Bond girls</h1>


<ul>
  <% current_page.data.bond_girls.each do |name| %>
    <li><%= name %></li>
  <% end %>
</ul>


<pre><code>
The YAML variables look just like a hash. You can access that local data through the **current_page** object: 
</code></pre>

<p>current_page.data.some_variable
```</p>

<p>You often use it to store tags, dates, titles and configuration options like which layout you wanna use for particular pages. Frontmatter is a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/YAML">YAML</a> store for your variables. You can also use <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JSON">JSON</a> if you prefer that. See, sounds way more complicated than it is. You can think of it as a place for putting data that could normally reside in a database—I mean obviously a very trimmed down version of that. I will discuss the various options and uses along the way when they come up.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ruby / Rails Code Smells 01]]></title>
    <link href="http://vis-kid.github.io/octopress_drafts_previewer/blog/2015/11/05/Code-Smells-01/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-05T04:29:10+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://vis-kid.github.io/octopress_drafts_previewer/blog/2015/11/05/Code-Smells-01</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/code_smells/code_smell_01.jpeg"></p>

<h3>Topics</h3>

<ul>
<li>Smelly Code</li>
<li>Large Class / God Class</li>
<li><p>Long Method</p></li>
<li><h3>Smelly Code</h3></li>
</ul>


<p>The following short series of articles is meant for slightly experienced Ruby developers and starters alike. I had the impression that code smells and their refactorings can be very daunting and intimidating to newbies—especially if they are not in the fortunate position to have mentors who can turn mystical programming concepts into shining light bulbs.</p>

<p>So what are we talking about exactly when people mention code smells? Is it always a problem in your code? Not necessarily! Can you avoid them completely? I don’t think so! Do you mean code smells lead to broken code? Well, sometimes and sometimes not. Should it be my priority to fix them right away? Same answer I fear, sometimes yes and sometimes you certainly should fry bigger fish first. Are you insane? Fair question at this point! Before you continue diving into this whole smelly business, remember to take away one thing from all of this: Don’t try to fix every smell you encounter—this is most certainly a waste of your time!</p>

<p>It seems to me that code smells are a bit hard to wrap up in a nicely labeled box. There are all kinds of smells with various different options to address them. Also, different programming languages and frameworks are prone to different kind of smells—but there are definitely a lot of common “genetic” strains among them. My attempt to describe code smells is to compare them with medical symptoms that tell you that you might have a problem. They can point to all sorts of latent problems and have a wide variety of solutions if diagnosed.</p>

<p>Thankfully they’re overall not as complicated as dealing with the human body—and psyche of course. Its a fair comparison though because some of these symptoms need to be treated right away and some others give you ample time to come up with a solution that is best for the “patient’s” overall well-being. If you have working code and you run into something smelly you’ll have to make the hard decision if its worth the time to find a fix and if that refactoring improves the stability of your app. That being said, if you stumble upon code which you can improve right away its good advice to leave the code behind a bit better than before—even a tiny bit better adds up substantially over time.</p>

<h4>Resistance</h4>

<p>The quality of your code becomes questionable if the inclusion of new code becomes harder—like deciding where to put new code is a pain or comes with a lot of ripple effects throughout your codebase for example. This is called resistance. As a guideline for code quality you can measure it always by how easy it is to introduce changes. If that is getting harder and harder its definitely time to refactor and to take the last part of <em>red-green-REFACTOR</em> more seriously in the future.</p>

<ul>
<li><h3>Large Class / God Class</h3></li>
</ul>


<p>Let’s start with something fancy sounding—“God classes”—because I think they are particular easy to grasp for beginners. God classes are a special case of a code smell called <strong>Large Class</strong>. In this section I’ll address both of them. If you have spent a little bit of time in Rails land you probably have seen them so often that they look normal to you.</p>

<p>You surely remember the “fat models, skinny controller” mantra? Well actually, skinny is good for all these classes but as a guideline its good advice for newbies I suppose. God classes are objects that attract all sorts of knowledge and behaviour like a black hole. Your usual suspects most often include the User model and whatever problem (hopefully ;) your app is trying to solve—first and foremost at least. A todo app might bulk up on the <strong>Todos</strong> model, a shopping app on <strong>Products</strong>, a photo app on <strong>Photos</strong>—you get the drift. People call them god classes because they know too much. They have too many connections with other classes—mostly because someone was modeling them lazily. It is hard work though to keep God classes in check. They make it really easy to dump more responsibilities onto them and as lots of greek heroes would attest, it takes a bit of skill to divide and conquer “gods”.</p>

<p>The problem with them is that they become harder and harder to understand, especially for new team members, harder to change and reuse becomes less and less of an option the more gravity they’ve amassed. Oh yeah, you’re right, your tests are unnecessarily harder to write as well. In short, there is not really an upside to having large classes and god classes in particular.</p>

<p>There are a couple of common symptoms / signs that your class needs some heroism / surgery:</p>

<ul>
<li>You need to scroll!</li>
<li>Tons of private methods?</li>
<li>Does your class have seven or more methods on it?</li>
<li>Hard to tell what your class really does—concisely!</li>
<li>Does your class have many reasons to change when your code evolves?</li>
</ul>


<p>Also, if you squint at your class and think “Eh? Ew!” you might be on to something too. If all that sounds familiar, chances are good that you found yourself a fine specimen.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class CastingInviter
  EMAIL_REGEX = /\A([^@\s]+)@((?:[-a-z0-9]+\.)+[a-z]{2,})\z/

  attr_reader :message, :invitees, :casting

  def initialize(attributes = {})
      @message  = attributes[:message]  || ''
      @invitees = attributes[:invitees] || ''
      @sender   = attributes[:sender]
      @casting  = attributes[:casting]
    end

    def valid?
      valid_message? &amp;&amp; valid_invitees?
    end

    def deliver
    if valid?
      invitee_list.each do |email|
        invitation = create_invitation(email)
        Mailer.invitation_notification(invitation, @message)
      end
      else
        failure_message  = "Your #{ @casting } message couldn’t be sent. Invitees emails or message are invalid"
        invitation = create_invitation(@sender)
      Mailer.invitation_notification(invitation, failure_message )
      end
    end

    private

    def invalid_invitees
      @invalid_invitees ||= invitee_list.map do |item|
      unless item.match(EMAIL_REGEX)
          item
        end
      end.compact
    end

    def invitee_list
      @invitee_list ||= @invitees.gsub(/\s+/, '').split(/[\n,;]+/)
    end

    def valid_message?
      @message.present?
    end

    def valid_invitees?
      invalid_invitees.empty?
    end

  def create_invitation(email)
    Invitation.create(
      casting:       @casting,
      sender:        @sender,
      invitee_email: email,
      status:        'pending'
    )
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>Ugly fella huh? Can you see how much nastyness is bundled in here? Of course I put a little cherry on top, but you will run into code like this sooner or later.  Let’s think about what responsibilities this <strong>CastingInviter</strong> class has to juggle.</p>

<ul>
<li>Delivering email</li>
<li>Checking for valid messages and email addresses</li>
<li>Getting rid of white space</li>
<li>Splitting email addresses on commas and semicolons</li>
</ul>


<p>Should all of this be dumped on a class which just wants to deliver a casting call via <strong>deliver</strong>? Certainly not! If your method of invitation changes you can expect to run into some <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shotgun_surgery">Shotgun surgery</a>. CastingInviter doesn’t need to know most of these details. That’s more the responsibility of some class that is specialized in dealing with email related stuff. In the future, you’ll find many reasons to change your code in here as well.</p>

<h3>Extract Class</h3>

<p>So how should we deal with this? Often, extracting a class is a handy refactoring pattern that will present itself as a reasonable solution to such problems as big, convoluted classes—especially when the class in question deals with multiple responsibilities. Private methods are often good candidates to start with—and easy marks as well. Sometimes you’ll need to extract even more than one class from such a bad boy—just don’t do it all in one step. Once you find enough coherent meat that seems to belong into a specialized object of its own you can extract that functionality into a new class.</p>

<p>You create a new class and gradually move the functionality over—one by one. Move each method separately and rename them if you see a reason to. Then reference the new class in the orignal one and delegate the needed functionality. Good thing you have test coverage (hopefully!) that lets you check if things still work properly every step of the way. Aim at being able to reuse your extracted classes as well. Its easier to see how its done in action so lets read some code:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class CastingInviter

  attr_reader :message, :invitees, :casting

  def initialize(attributes = {})
    @message  = attributes[:message]  || ''
    @invitees = attributes[:invitees] || ''
    @casting  = attributes[:casting]
    @sender   = attributes[:sender]
  end

  def valid?
    casting_email_handler.valid?
  end

  def deliver
    casting_email_handler.deliver
  end

  private

  def casting_email_handler
    @casting_email_handler = CastingEmailHandler.new(
      message:  message, 
      invitees: invitees, 
      casting:  casting, 
      sender:   @sender
    )
  end
end
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="ruby">class CastingEmailHandler 
  EMAIL_REGEX = /\A([^@\s]+)@((?:[-a-z0-9]+\.)+[a-z]{2,})\z/

  def initialize(attr = {})
    @message  = attr[:message]  || ''
    @invitees = attr[:invitees] || ''
    @casting  = attr[:casting]
    @sender   = attr[:sender]
  end

  def valid?
    valid_message? &amp;&amp; valid_invitees?
  end

  def deliver
    if valid?
      invitee_list.each do |email|
        invitation = create_invitation(email)
        Mailer.invitation_notification(invitation, @message)
      end
    else
      failure_message  = "Your #{ @casting } message couldn’t be sent. Invitees emails or message are invalid"
      invitation = create_invitation(@sender)
      Mailer.invitation_notification(invitation, failure_message )
    end
  end

  private

  def invalid_invitees
    @invalid_invitees ||= invitee_list.map do |item|
      unless item.match(EMAIL_REGEX)
        item
      end
    end.compact
  end

  def invitee_list
    @invitee_list ||= @invitees.gsub(/\s+/, '').split(/[\n,;]+/)
  end

  def valid_invitees?
    invalid_invitees.empty?
  end

  def valid_message?
    @message.present?
  end

  def create_invitation(email)
    Invitation.create(
      casting:       @casting,
      sender:        @sender,
      invitee_email: email,
      status:        'pending'
    )
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>In this solution, you’ll not only see how this separation of concerns affects your code quality, it also reads a lot better and becomes easier to digest. Here we delegate methods to a new class that is specialized in dealing with delivering these invitations via email. You have one dedicated place that checks if the messages and invitees are valid and how they need to be delivered. <strong>CastingInviter</strong> doesn’t need to know anything about these details so we delegate these responsibilities to a new class <strong>CastingEmailHandler</strong>.</p>

<p>The knowledge of how to deliver and check for validity of these casting invitation emails is now all contained in our new extracted class. Do we have more code now? You bet! Was it worth it to separate concerns? Pretty sure! Can we go beyond that and refactor <strong>CastingEmailHandler</strong> some more? Absolutely! Knock yourself out!</p>

<p>In case you’re wondering about the <strong>valid?</strong> method on <strong>CastingEmailHandler</strong> and <strong>CastingInviter</strong>. This one is for RSpec to create a custom matcher. This lets me write something like</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">expect(casting_inviter).to be_valid
</code></pre>

<p>Pretty handy I think.</p>

<p>There are more techniques for dealing with large classes / god objects and over the course of this series you’ll learn a couple of ways to refactor such objects. There is no fixed prescription how you need to deal with these cases—it always depends and its a case-by-case judgement call if you need to bring the big guns or if smaller, incremental refactoring techniques oblige best. I know, a bit frustrating at times. Following the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Single_responsibility_principle">Single Responsibility Principle</a> (SRP) will go a long way though and is a good nose to follow.</p>

<ul>
<li><h3>Long Method</h3></li>
</ul>


<p>Having methods that got a little big is one of the most common things you encounter as a developer. In general, you want to know at a glance what a method is supposed to do. It should also have only one level of nesting or one level of abstraction. In short, avoid to write complicated methods. I know this sounds hard and it often is. A solution that comes up frequently is extracting parts of the method into one or more new functions. This refactoring technique is called <strong>extract method</strong>—its one of the simplest but none the less very effective. As a nice side effect, your code becomes more readable if you name your methods appropriately.</p>

<p>Let’s take a look at feature specs where you’ll need this technique a lot. I remember getting introduced to <em>extract method</em> while writing such feature specs and how amazing it felt when the lightbulb went on. Because feature specs like this are easy to understand they are a good candiate for demonstration. Plus you’ll run into similar scenarios over and over when you write your specs.</p>

<p><strong>spec/features/some_feature_spec.rb</strong></p>

<pre><code class="ruby">require 'rails_helper'

feature 'M marks mission as complete' do
  scenario 'successfully' do
    visit_root_path
    fill_in      'Email', with: 'M@mi6.com'
    click_button 'Submit'
    visit missions_path
    click_on     'Create Mission' 
    fill_in      'Mission Name', with: 'Project Moonraker'
    click_button 'Submit'

    within "li:contains('Project Moonraker')" do
      click_on 'Mission completed'
    end

    expect(page).to have_css 'ul.missions li.mission-name.completed', text: 'Project Moonraker'
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>As you can easily see, there is a lot going on in this scenario. You go to the index page, sign in and create a mission for the setup, then exercise via marking the mission as complete and finally you verify the behaviour. No rocket science, but also not clean and definitely not composed for reuseability. We can do better than that:</p>

<p><strong>spec/features/some_feature_spec.rb</strong></p>

<pre><code class="ruby">require 'rails_helper'

feature 'M marks mission as complete' do
  scenario 'successfully' do
    sign_in_as 'M@mi6.com'
    create_classified_mission_named 'Project Moonraker'

    mark_mission_as_complete        'Project Moonraker'

    agent_sees_completed_mission    'Project Moonraker'
  end
end

def create_classified_mission_named(mission_name)
    visit missions_path
    click_on     'Create Mission' 
    fill_in      'Mission Name', with: mission_name
    click_button 'Submit'
    end

def mark_mission_as_complete(mission_name)
    within "li:contains('#{mission_name}')" do
      click_on 'Mission completed'
    end
end

def agent_sees_completed_mission(mission_name)
    expect(page).to have_css 'ul.missions li.mission-name.completed', text: mission_name
end

def sign_in_as(email)
    visit root_path
    fill_in      'Email', with: email
    click_button 'Submit'
end
</code></pre>

<p>Here we extracted four methods that can be easily reused in other tests now. I hope its clear that we hit three birds with one stone. The feature is a lot more consise, it reads better and is made up of extracted components without duplication. Let’s imagine you’d have written all kinds of similar scenarios without extracting these methods and you want to change some implementation. Now you wish you’d taken the time to refactor your tests and have one central place to apply your changes.</p>

<p>Sure there is an even better way to deal with feature specs like this—Page Objects for example—but that’s not our scope for today. I guess that’s all you need to know about extracting methods. You can apply this refactoring pattern everywhere in your code—not only in specs of course. In terms of fequency of use, my guess is that it will be your number one technique to improve the quality of your code. Have fun!</p>

<ul>
<li><h3>Parameter Object</h3></li>
</ul>


<p>Let’s close this article with an example how you can slim down your parameters. It gets tedious pretty fast when you have to feed your methods more than one or two arguments. Wouldn’t it be nice to drop in one object instead? That’s exactly what you can do if you introduce a parameter object.</p>

<p>All these parameters are not only a pain to write and to keep in order, it can also lead to code duplication—and we certainly want to avoid that wherever possible. What I like especially about this refactoring technique is how this affects other methods inside as well. You often are able to get rid of a lot of parameter junk down in the foodchain as well.</p>

<p>Let’s go over this simple example. M can assign a new mission and needs needs a mission name, an agent, an objective and is also able to switch between double 0 status—meaning their licence to kill.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class M
  def assign_new_mission(mission_name, agent_name, objective, licence_to_kill: nil)
    print "Mission #{mission_name} has been assigned to #{agent_name} with the objective to #{objective}."
    if licence_to_kill
      print " The licence to kill has been granted."
    else
      print "The licence to kill has not been granted."
    end
  end
end

m = M.new
m.assign_new_mission('Octopussy', 'James Bond', 'find the nuclear device', licence_to_kill: true)
# =&gt; Mission Octopussy has been assigned to James Bond with the objective to find the nuclear device. The licence to kill has been granted. 
</code></pre>

<p>When you look at this and ask what happens when the mission “parameters” grow in complexity then you’re already onto something. That’s a pain point that you can only solve if you pass in a single object that has all the information you need. More often than not, this also helps you to stay away from changing the method if the parameter object changes for some reason.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class Mission
  attr_reader :mission_name, :agent_name, :objective, :licence_to_kill

  def initialize(mission_name: mission_name, agent_name: agent_name, objective: objective, licence_to_kill: licence_to_kill)
      @mission_name    = mission_name
      @agent_name      = agent_name
      @objective       = objective
      @licence_to_kill = licence_to_kill
    end

    def assign
      print "Mission #{mission_name} has been assigned to #{agent_name} with the objective to #{objective}."
      if licence_to_kill
        print " The licence to kill has been granted."
      else
        print " The licence to kill has not been granted."
      end
    end
end

class M
  def assign_new_mission(mission)
      mission.assign
    end
end

m = M.new
mission = Mission.new(mission_name: 'Octopussy', agent_name: 'James Bond', objective: 'find the nuclear device', licence_to_kill: true)
m.assign_new_mission(mission)
# =&gt; Mission Octopussy has been assigned to James Bond with the objective to find the nuclear device. The licence to kill has been granted.
</code></pre>

<p>So we created a new object, <strong>Mission</strong>, that is soley focused on providing <strong>M</strong> with the information needed to assign a new mission and provide #<strong>assign_new_mission</strong> with a singular paramter object. No need to pass in these pesky parameters yourself. Instead you tell the object to reveal the information you need inside the method itself. Additionally, we also extracted some behaviour—the information how to print—into the new <strong>Mission</strong> object.</p>

<p>Why should <strong>M</strong> need to know about how to print mission assignments? The new #<strong>assign</strong> also benefitted from extraction by loosing some weight because we didn’t need to pass in the parameter object—so no need to write stuff like <strong>mission.mission_name</strong>, <strong>mission.agent_name</strong> and so on. Now we just use our <strong>attr_reader</strong>(s) which is much cleaner than without the extraction. You dig? What’s also handy about this is that <strong>Mission</strong> might collect all sorts of additional methods or states that are nicely encapsulated in one place and ready for you to access.</p>

<p>With this technique you’ll end up with methods that are more concise, they tend to read better and you avoid repeating the same group of parameters all over the place. Pretty good deal! Getting rid of identical groups of parameters is also an important strategy for DRY code. Try to look out for extracting more than just your data. If you can place behaviour in the new class as well you’ll have objects that are more useful—otherwise they’ll quickly start to smell as well.</p>

<p>Sure, most of the time you’ll run into more complicated versions of that—and your tests will certainly also need to be adapted simultaneously during such refactorings—but if you have that simple example under your belt you’ll be ready for action.</p>

<p>I’m gonna watch the new Bond now. Heard its not that good though…
Update: Saw Spectre. My verdict: compared to Skyfall—which was MEH imho—Spectre was wawawiwa!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
